<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc private="RFC X____" ?>
<rfc ipr="none" category="bcp" docName="recommendation-for-assembly-syntactics">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Assembly Syntactics">0xSCA: Standards Committee Assembly</title>

        <author fullname="Jos Kuijpers" initials="J.C." role="editor"
        surname="Kuijpers">
            <organization>Jarvix</organization>

            <address>
                <email>jos@kuijpersvof.nl (contact for any inquiries)</email>
                <uri>http://www.jarvix.org/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Marian Beermann" initials="M.B." role="editor"
            surname="Beermann">
            <address>
                <email>public@enkore.de</email>
                <uri>http://www.enkore.de/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date month="April" year="2012" />
        <area>ASM</area>
        <workgroup>0x10c Standards Committee</workgroup>
        <abstract>
          <t>This document describes an assembly and preprocessor syntax
          suitable for the DCPU-16 environment. This syntax is called the
          0xSCA, or Standards Committee Assembly.</t>
          <t>This is not a standard.</t>
        </abstract>
      </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
          <t>This documents describes 0xSCA, Standards Committee Assembly. It
          is a definition of a syntax to be used for writing assembly for the
          DCPU-16 processor. Use of this syntax is voluntarily. With 0xSCA,
          there is a defined syntax, and could decrease code incompatibility
          among compilers.</t>
          <t>Again, to be clear: 0xSCA is a syntax definition, not a standard.
          0xSCA is to DCPU-16, what AT&amp;T or the NASM syntax is to IA-32.</t>

          <section title="Requirements Language">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
            "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
            document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
            target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Document Markup">
            <section title="Indentation and whitespace">
                <t>Whitespace MUST be allowed between all
                elements of a line, including but not limited to opcodes, values,
                syntactic characters and preprocessor directives. Both a space
                (' ' U+0020) and a tab (U+0009) are considered whitespace
                characters.</t>
                <t>Indenting instructions is RECOMMENDED. NOT indenting
                labels and preprocessor directives RECOMMENDED. The assembler
                MUST NOT mandate indentation to assemble successfully.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Case sensitivity">
            <t>Assemblers MUST accept everything without regard to case EXCEPT
            string and character literals.</t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Preprocessor Markup">
            <section title="Comments">
                <t>Comments are used to add information to the code, making it
                more readable and understandable. Comments can consist any
                character in any combination. This document specifies one-line
                comments only.</t>
                <t>Any characters following and in the same line of a semicolon
                (; U+003B) are    comments and MUST be ignored, except when the
                semicolon resides within  the representation of a string. In
                that case, the semicolon MUST NOT be treated as a comment.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Prefix">
                <t>Every preprocessor directive starts with an identifier. This
                identifier is used to distinguish preprocessor directives from
                other code.</t>
                <t>For historical reasons, directives can either start with a dot
                (. U+002E) or a number sign (# U+0023).</t>
                <t>Preprocessor directives MUST start with a dot (. U+002E) or a 
                number sign (# U+0023).</t>
                <t>Using a dot is RECOMMENDED to distinguish between C preprocessor
                syntax.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Directives">
                <t>All directives in this section MUST be handled in order and
                in recognition of their position. For the purpose of this document,
                a dot (.) is used to describe preprocessor directives.</t>
                <section title="Inclusion">
                    <section title="Code">
                        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.include "file"
.include <file>]]></artwork></figure>
                        <t>The former directive MUST include the file into the
                        current file. The path is relative to the current file.
                        The assembler SHOULD report to the user if the given
                        filename does not exist and continue assembly.</t>
                        <t>The latter includes the file from an implementation
                        defined location, which may not even exist but trigger
                        certain behaviour, i.e. inclusion of intrinsics.</t>
                    </section>
                    <section title="Binary">
                        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.incbin "file"
.incbin <file>]]></artwork></figure>
                        <t>incbin MUST include the specified binary as raw,
                        unprocessed data, the path to the file is relative 
                        from the current file. All labels behind this directive
                        MUST be offset by the size of the file.</t>
                        <t>The latter form of incbin MUST include the file from
                        an implementation defined location.</t>
                    </section>
                </section>
                <section title="Definitions">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.def name [value]
.define name [value]
.equ name value
.undef name]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>def/define/equ MUST assign the constant value to name. If the value
                    is omitted, the literal 1 (one) MUST be assumed.</t>
                    <t>undef MUST remove the given symbol from the namespace.
                    If the given symbol does not exist compilation SHOULD
                    continue and a warning MAY be emitted.</t>
                    <t>Any occurrences of the definition during its existence,
                    MUST be replaced with the given value to the definition.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Data insertion">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.dw value [,value...]
.dp value [,value...]
.fill count[,value]
.ascii [flags][<value>]"string"]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>dw (data word) MUST store the values literally and unpacked at the
                    location of the directive.</t>
                    <t>dp (data pack) MUST pack pairs of values into a single word. The
                    first value is placed into the high octet, and the second is placed
                    into the low octet of the word. Should there be an odd number of
                    values after a dp declaration, the remaining octet MUST be filled
                    with the value 0.</t>
                    <t>fill (fill words) MUST insert a count of words, initialized to the
                    specified value.  If the value is not provided, the assembler MUST
                    assume 0.</t>
                    <t>ascii (ascii string) MUST pack the ascii values of the string as 
                    described by the flags that precede it. An explanation of the flags 
                    is provided in the section on ascii flags.<xref target="ascii_flags"/></t>
                    <t>The optional value parameter in between less than (&lt; U+003C) 
                    and greater than (&gt; U+003E) will be bitwise ORed with each character 
                    in the string.  The upper octet for unpacked strings will default to 
                    all 0's before the bitwise OR.</t>
                    <section title="Ascii Literal Flags" anchor="ascii_flags">
                        <t>k: The ascii values are "packed." Each character is mapped to an
                        octet of data. These are written in order. Certain other flags
                        may place octets that precede the first character's octet.</t>
                        <t>s: The ascii values are "packed" and "swapped." Like k, each
                        character uses one octet, however the order of the octets is
                        reversed within each word. Flags k and s are incompatible with
                        each other. Certain other flags may place octets before the first
                        character octet.</t>
                        <t>z: Zero terminate the string, inheriting character width. A null
                        character will be appended to the string. If the string is one of
                        the packed formats only one octet will be added, where unpacked
                        strings will have a full word of zero. For the purpose of
                        determining string length, this zero counts as one character.</t>
                        <t>x: Word Zero terminate the string. This will zero terminate the
                        string, forcing a zero word onto the end of the string. If the
                        string is packed and of an odd length, a zero octet will be 
                        placed at the end of the content, before the zero word. For the 
                        purpose of determining string length, this zero will add quantity
                        of zero octets added divided by the octet width of each character.</t>
                        <t>For example, an unpacked string will always have 1 added to the
                        string length by the Z flag. A packed string of odd length will
                        have 3 added to the string length, where an even length packed
                        string will have 2 added to the length;</t>
                        <t>Flags w and x are incompatible.</t>
                        <t>a: Octet Pascal Length. This will prepend the length of the string
                        as an octet to the string content. This is only compatible with 
                        a packed mode, either k or s. (For swapped mode, this will end
                        up being the lower (second) octet of the first word.)</t>
                        <t>p: Word Pascal Length. This will prepend the length of the string
                        as a full word to the string content. This is compatible with 
                        either packed or unpacked modes. Flags a and p are incompatible.</t>
                    </section>
                   
                </section>
                <section title="Origin relocation">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.org address]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>The org preprocessor directive MUST take an address
                    as the only argument. Assemblers SHOULD verify the
                    address is 16-bit sized. Assembler MUST add this
                    address to the address of all labels, creating a
                    relocation of the program.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Macros: macro block and macro insertion">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.macro name([param [,param...]])
    code
.end
name([param [,param...]])]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>The macro directive defines a macro, a parameterized block
                    of code that can be inserted any time later. Parameters,
                    if any, are written in parentheses separated by commas (,).</t>
                    <t>Using the name with parentheses MUST insert a formerly defined
                    macro and expands the parameters of the macro with the
                    comma-separated parameters following the name of the macro to
                    insert.</t>
                    <t>Parameter substitutions can only be constant values and
                    memory references. Preprocessor directives inside the macro
                    MUST be handled upon insertion, not definition.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Repeat block">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.rep times
    code
.end]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>The code in the repeat-block MUST be repeated the number
                    of times specified. 'times' MUST be a positive integer.
                    Preprocessor directives inside the repeat-block MUST be
                    handled when the repetition is complete, to make allow
                    conditional repetitions.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Conditionals">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.if expression
    codeTrue
.elif expression
    codeElseTrue
.elseif expression
    codeElseTrue
.else
    codeElse
.end
.ifdef definition
.ifndef definition
isdef(definition)]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>For the definition of valid expressions, see
                    <xref target="ia" />.</t>
                    <t>The if clause is REQUIRED. The else clause is OPTIONAL.
                    The elif/elseif clause is OPTIONAL and can occur multiple times.</t>
                    <t>If expression consists of a single constant value,
                    then expression = 1 MUST be assumed. If expression evaluates
                    to 1, the codeTrue-block MUST be assembled. When the
                    evaluation fails, the next elif block must be evaluated. In
                    any other case codeElse, if an else clause is specified,
                    MUST be assembled.</t>
                    <t>isdef(symbol) can be used in place of expression.
                    isdef MUST evaluate to 1 if the given symbol is currently
                    defined, else it MUST evaluate to 0.</t>
                    <t>ifdef is short for if isdef(). ifndef is short for if !isdef()</t>
                    <t>Nesting of if directives MUST be supported.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Error reporting">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.error message]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>Triggers an assembler error with the message, stopping
                    execution of the assembler. The message SHOULD be shown in
                    combination with the filename and line number.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Alignment">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.align boundary]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>Aligns code or data on doubleword or other boundary.</t>
                    <t>The assembler MUST add zeroed words (0x0000) to the generated
                    machinecode until the alignment is correct. The number of
                    words inserted can be calculated using the formula:
                    'boundary - (currentPosition modulo boundary)'.</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Echo general output">
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
.echo message]]></artwork></figure>
                    <t>The echo directive can be used to inform the user about
                    (possible) issues, progress, etc.</t>
                    <t>The assembler SHOULD report the message to the user.</t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
    
        <section title="Tokenizer Markup">
            <section title="Labels">
                <t>Labels MUST be single-worded identifiers containing only
                alphabetical characters (/[A-Za-z]/), numbers (/[0-9]/),
                underscores (_ U+005F), and periods(. U+002E). The label MUST represent
                the address of following instruction or data. A label MUST NOT start with a
                number, an underscore or a period. A label SHOULD end with a colon (: U+003A), but
                starting with a colon MAY be supported. A label MUST NOT end with a period.</t>
                <t>Local labels MUST start with an underscore (_ U+002E) and end
                with a colon (: U+003A). Local labels MUST be scoped between the
                surrounding global labels. Local labels in different scopes
                MUST be able to have the same name.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Inline character literals">
                <t>A character surrounded by apostrophes (' U+0029) MUST be
                interpreted as its corresponding 7-bit ASCII value in a word
                (LSB).</t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Inline arithmetic" anchor="ia">
            <t>Source code can include inline arithmetics anywhere a
            constant value is permitted. Inline arithmetic may only
            consist of + (addition), - (subtraction), * (multiplication), /
            (integer division), % (modulus) and ! (negation), parentheses may be used
            to group expressions.</t>
            <t>The following bitwise operators MUST also be supported: &amp;
            (bit-wise AND) ^ (bit-wise XOR), | (bit-wise OR), ~ (bit-wise NOT), &lt;&lt;
            and &gt;&gt; (bit-wise shifts).
            </t>
            <t>The following logical and bitwise operators MUST also be
            supported: == (equal), != (not equal, also &lt;&gt;),
            &lt; (smaller than), &gt; (greater than), &lt;= (smaller or
            equal), &gt;= (greater or equal), &amp; (bit-wise AND) ^
            (bit-wise XOR), | (bit-wise OR), &amp;&amp; (logical AND), ||
            (logical OR), ^^ (logical XOR) which MUST be evaluated with
            respect to this order.</t>
            <t>Inline arithmetic MUST be evaluated as soon as possible, 
            the result MUST be used as a literal value in place of the expression.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Conformance">
            <section title="Recognition of conformance">
                <t>An assembler, formatter and any other assembly related
                program that is fully compliant to 0xSCA MAY label itself
                "0xSCA compatible". When using this label, the subject SHOULD
                include a note of the version of the RFC it is written against.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

    <section title="Design Rationale">
        <section title="Labels">
            <t>Although Notch used the syntax :label in his first
            examples, it is not common in any popular assembler.
            Thus we decided for label: as the recommended form,
            still silently allowing the deprecated form.</t>
            <t>To simplify writing reusable code we also introduced
            local labels, which are only visible from within the
            global label they are defined within. Implementing this
            is easy to do and introduces little overhead, as nesting
            is neither specified nor recommended.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Preprocessor">
            <t>0xSCA allows many operators and even parentheses in
            expressions for if-clauses, which complicates the
            implementation of these. We do recognize that, but
            the actual implementation difficulty is not too high,
            as there are many examples how to achieve this and
            we think that the additional power and reduced
            code complexity, resulting in better maintainable
            code, is worth the effort.</t>
            <t>The ability to define custom constants inline is
            easy to implement and yields more easily maintainable
            code, while introducing a minimum of additional syntax.</t>
            <t>Both kinds of file inclusion support two different
            forms, one including the file relative to the current file,
            and the other including it from an implementation defined
            location. The former is ideal for splitting a program
            in multiple parts, while the latter is intended for
            implementation-provided resources such as source level
            libraries.</t>
            <t>A preprocessor must accept every directive with
            a dot (.) or a number sign (#) prefix. While Notch seems
            to prefer the latter, the former is much more common
            among todays assemblers. Thus we decided to support
            both, especially as the implementation-side overhead is
            very low.</t>
        </section>
    </section>
        
        <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>This memo has no applicable security considerations.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
            <reference anchor="GHBP" target="https://github.com/blog/1098-take-over-the-galaxy-with-github">
              <front>
                <title>Take Over The Galaxy with GitHub</title>
                <author fullname="Vincent Marti" initials="V" surname="Marti" />
                <date month="April" year="2012" />
              </front>
            </reference>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>