<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private="RFC X1005 (Draft-Lib)"?>
<rfc ipr="none" number="1005" category="std" docName="draft-string-format">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="String Format">String Format</title>
		
		<author initials="M.S." surname="Schuetze" fullname="Malte Schuetze">
			<address>
				<email>malte.schuetze@fgms.de</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		
		<date month="April" year="2012"/>
		<area>Lib</area>
		<workgroup>0x10c Standards Committee</workgroup>
		<keyword>String</keyword>
		<keyword>String Format</keyword>
		<keyword>Library Specifications</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>This document presents a general format for strings in 
			libraries intended to be shared across programs and with 
			other users.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	
	<middle>
		<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
			<t>Shared Libraries depend on certain formats being given. 
			Strings, being a common argument type for cross-library 
			calls, should therefore be standardized. Length-prefixed 
			strings are to be used for security and efficiency reasons.</t>
			
			<section anchor="intro-lang" title="Requirements Language">
				<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", 
				"SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", 
				"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document 
				are to be interpreted as described in <xref 
				target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
			</section>
			<section anchor="intro-terms" title="Used Terms">
				<t>
				<list style="symbols">
				<t>"String" or "string" refers to a sequence of 
				characters of variable length.</t>
				<t>"P-string", "pstring" or "length-prefixed string" 
				refers to an 8-bit value representing the length of the 
				following string, followed by n characters of length n, 
				where n is the value of the length-prefix.</t>
				<t>"C-string", "cstring" or "null-terminated string" 
				refers to a sequence of characters that may not include 
				the character with the value 0, followed by the 
				character with value 0 (also known as "null-terminator" 
				or "null character")</t>
				<t>"Character" or "character" refers to a group of 
				bits representing a letter, a number, a punctuation 
				mark, or a control character. A control character is a 
				non-printable character that influences the text.</t>
				<t>"Word" or "word" refers to a group of 16 bits
				representing a value. A word is the smallest addressable
				space in the DCPU.</t>
				<t>"Library" or "library" refers to a group of 
				functions that are used across different programs.</t>
				<t>"Program" or "program" refers to a sequence of 
				machine instructions for the DCPU.</t>
				<t>"User" or "user" refers to any person using or 
				creating a program.</t>
				</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section anchor="structure" title="Structure of P-Strings">
			<t>A P-string is composed of a 16-bit length prefix and a 
			sequence of n characters where n is the value of the prefix.
			</t>
			<t>P-string = n (nCHAR)</t>
			<t>The prefix for such a string MUST be present and MUST 
			represent the exact number of following characters.</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="rationale" title="Rationale for using P-Strings">
		<section anchor="rationale-benefits" title="Benefits of P-Strings">
			<t>The rationale for using P-strings is a simple matter of
			weighing benefits against disadvantages. Note that this is
			not a normative rationale, but one developed by the
			Standards Committee with focus on the DCPU design.</t>
			<t>
			<list style='symbols'>
				<t>Accessing the length of the string is O(1) fast.</t>
				<t>Buffer overflows are prevented by being able to 
				allocate enough space ahead of time.
					<list style='symbols'>
						<t>This also increases the security of programs 
						by preventing arbitrary shell code from being
						executed.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>The null-character can be used in strings, while 
				using it in a C-string would terminate the string.</t>
				<t>The runtime cost of P-string concatenation is O(n), 
				while the runtime cost of C-string concatenation is 
				O(n+m).</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="rationale-disadvantages" title="Disadvantages of P-Strings">
			<t>
			<list style='symbols'>
				<t>Indexing begins at 1 instead of 0.</t>
				<t>Fixed-length strings still require a prefixed length word.</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		</section>
		<section anchor="notes" title="Other Notes">
			<t>
			<list style='symbols'>
				<t>Since the smallest addressable size in the DCPU is a
				word (16 bits), this effectively allows a maximum string
				length of 65536 characters without any loss in
				efficiency.</t>
				<t>Cutting off the beginning of a string is more 
				expensive for P-strings, but cutting off the end is 
				more expensive for C-strings. (Other solutions are 
				possible, but introduce memory leaks.) Therefore, the 
				two arguments negate each other.</t>
				<t>The names P-string and C-string come from Pascal and
				C, which use the respective format.</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="packed-strings" title="Packed P-Strings">
			<t>The current implementation of characters in the DCPU
			effectively leaves the high 8 bits empty. It is therefore
			possible to store two characters in one word. Such packed
			strings are outside the scope of this RFC.</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>Using P-strings reduces the risk of arbitrary shell 
			code being executed by overflowing the input buffer. 
			However, hidden instructions in the string may be executed 
			later when the sections are not cleared and the stack or 
			instruction pointer is moved there. Measures should be 
			taken by the user to ensure this does not happen.</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	
	<back>
		<references title="References">
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>
