<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc private="RFC X1004 (Draft-Lib)" ?>
<rfc ipr="none" number="1004" category="info" docName="draft-specification-standard-math-library">

	<front>
		<title abbrev="Standardized Math Library">Standardized Math Library</title>
		<author fullname="Matthew Edgmon" initials="M.E." role="editor"
            surname="Edgmon">
			<organization>The ACC</organization>
			<address>
				<email>matthewedgmon@gmail.com</email>
				<uri>https://github.com/MatthewEdgmon</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date day="8th" month="April" year="2012" />
		<area>Lib</area>
		<workgroup>0x10c Standards Committee</workgroup>
		<abstract>
			<t>This draft is being purposed to provide basic math functions 
			that should be present in all machines, along with very arbitrary 
			calling names that should never interfere with programs already 
			on the machine.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
	
	<section title="Introduction and Purpose">
		<t>The purposing of this document to the 0x10c standards commitee
		is to make the proposal for a standard math library, which if the
		authors of vital utilites such as compilers and assemblers make a
		standardized library in the future, a math library such as this
		would be nessacary. Usage of these standardized implmentations of
		the math functions would also have the advantage of being equally
		accurate. Two machines would receive the same result for a Sine
		function.</t>
		
		<t>The author of this draft has worked on a library for such this
		purpose and would like to recomend it to the commitee as the 
		library of choice for the topic of this document. The author
		recomends FooMath (https://github.com/MatthewEdgmon/FooMath).</t>
	</section>
			
	<section title="Requirements Language">
		<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
		"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
		document are to be interpreted and understood as described in <xref
		target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Features">
		<t>FooMath contains functions for working with 16 to 64 bit integers.
		It includes Sine, Cosine, Tangenent, Exponents, Square Roots, and basic
		math routines. However usage of the basic math routines for 16-bits acts
		only as a reference-wrapper function and should not be used.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Advantages">
		<t>The advantages of adopting a standardized arithmetics library
		now far outweigh the cons. If adopted, then mathematics heavy
		applications (such as those for finding distance between you and
		a rock mine for example) have a common ground in their calculating.
		If the focus of optimizing was spent only on this one library, the
		amount of time spent on individual apllications optimizing and
		debugging can be kept to a minimum. Another advantage is that
		creating a standard library like in C/C++ would have a big task
		of rewritting all of the math functions. Creating and editing one
		now would decrease the load work on creating one later, when such
		a proposal is already underway.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Disadvantages">
		<t>There are no disadvantages. Time spent working on the library by
		the author serves only as a minor inconvience at best.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Standardized Usage">
		<t>Usage of the library as a source file for use in programs for the
		DCPU-16 should be made to follow these guidelines. The first guideline
		is to only use the first callable label of a function. Dissecting the
		source and looking for mid-function labels to jump to is prohibited
		and invalidates the standardized usage.</t>
		
		<t>All functions of the library return in A, per commitee standards,
		and all functions save working registers before executing. If any parts
		of the library are found to be incompatable with the commitee's ABI, please
		alert the author.</t>
		
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="additional-notes" title="Additional Notes">
		<t>If FooMath is not a desired choice by the commitee, the author
		asks it be put on temporarily, and then edited/replaced with a more
		desired one for whatever reason.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
		<t>This memo has no applicable security considerations.</t>
	</section>
	
	</middle>
	
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2629.xml"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3552.xml"?>
		</references>
	</back>
	
</rfc>